JOHN: Sherlock!
Its a trick.
Just a magic trick.
No. All right, stop it now.
Now, stay exactly where you are.
Dont move.' All right.
Keep your eyes fixed on me.
Please, would you
do this for me?
Do what?
This phone call, its er...
...its my note.
Its what people do, don't they?
Leave a note.
Leave a note when?
Goodbye, John.
No. Dont...
Sherlock!
(JOHN MOANS)
John.
John, look at me. Look at me.
And sleep.
Right the way down, right the way
deep, right the way, sound asleep.
Thats real.
Thats good, with my voice just
there in the centre of your head
and floating all the
way around you.
And you will awaken
in three, two, one...
...zero.
Let me come through please!
Hes my friend.
LESTRADE: Bollocks!
No, no, no, no, its obvious.
Thats how he did it.
Its obvious.
Derren Brown?! Let it
go, Sherlocke dead.
But is he?
There was a body, it was him.
It was definitely him,
Molly Hooper laid him out.
No, shes lying.
It was Jim Moriartys
body with a mask on.
A mask?
A bungee rope, a
mask, Derren Brown.
Two years and the theories
keep getting more stupid.
How many more have you
got for me today?
Well, you know the paving
slabs in that whole area,
even the exact ones
that he landed on,
you know they were all... Guilt!
Thats all this is.
You pushed us all into thinking
that Sherlock that was a
fraud, you and Donovan.
You did this and it killed
him and hes staying dead.
Do you honestly believe that if
you have enough stupid theories,
its going to change
what really happened?
I believe in Sherlock Holmes.
Yeah, well, that
wont bring him back.
And that after extensive
police investigations...
Richard Brook did indeed prove to be
the creation of James Moriarty...
MALE REPORTER: Amidst unprecedented
scenes, there was uproar in court
as Sherlock Holmes was vindicated
and cleared of all suspicion.
FEMALE REPORTER: Sadly, all this
comes too late for the Detective,
who became something of a
celebrity two years ago.
Questions are now being asked as to
why police let matters get so far.
Sherlock Holmes
fell to his death
from the top of Londons Barts
Hospital. Although he left no note,
friends say its unlikely he
was able to cope with the...
Well then. Absent friends.
Sherlock.
And may God rest his soul.
(HELICOPTER FLIES OVER)
(HEAVY BREATHING)
(MAN SPEAKS IN SERBIAN)
(MEN SHOUT IN SERBIAN)
(DOGS BARK)
(BARKING GETS CLOSER)
(GUNSHOTS)
(LOUD MUSIC THROUGH HEADPHONES)
(THUMP)
(MAN GROANS)
(THUMPS CONTINUE)
(MAN SPEAKS IN SERBIAN)
(THUMPS AND SHOUTING CONTINUE)
(MAN GROANS)
(TRANSLATED FROM SERBIAN)
(PRISONER WHISPERS)
What?
(DOOR CLOSES)
Now listen to me.
Theres an underground terrorist
network active in London
and a massive
attack is imminent.
Sorry, but the
holiday is over...
...Brother dear.
Back to Baker Street...
...Sherlock Holmes.
CHILD: Penny for the guy?
Oi, mate, penny for the guy?
Penny for the guy, mate?
Penny for the guy?
JOHN: That was the most
ridiculous thing Ive ever done.
SHERLOCK: You invaded
Afghanistan.
(DOOR OPENS)
(HE CLEARS HIS THROAT)
You have been busy, havent you?
Quite the busy little bee. Hmm.
Moriartys network. Took me
two years to dismantle it.
And youre confident you have?
The Serbian side was the
last piece of the puzzle.
Yes. You got yourself in deep
there with Baron Maupertuis.
Quite a scheme. Colossal.
Anyway. Youre safe now.
Mmm.
A small "thank you"
wouldnt go amiss.
What for?
For wading in.
In case youve forgotten, field
work is not my natural milieu.
"Wading in?"
You sat there and watched
me being beaten a pulp.
I got you out. No, I got me out.
Why didn't you intervene sooner?
I couldnt risk giving
myself away, could I?
It would have ruined everything.
You were enjoying it. Nonsense.
Definitely enjoying it.
Listen, do you have any idea
what it was like, Sherlock,
going undercover?
Smuggling my way into
their ranks like that?
The noise, the people!
I didn't know you spoke Serbian.
I didn't. But the language
has a Slavic root.
Frequent Turkish and
German loan words.
Took me a couple of hours.
Hmm, youre slipping.
Middle-age, brother mine.
Comes to us all.
(DOOR OPENS)
Oh, no, you don't
take it, do you?
No. You forget a little
thing like that.
Yes.
You forget lots of
little things, it seems.
Uh-huh.
Not sure about that.
Hmm? Ages you.
Just trying it out.
Well, it ages you.
Look... Im not your mother,
Ive no right to expect it...
No... But just one
phone call, John!
Just one phone call
would have done.
I know.
After all we went through!
Yes.
I am sorry.
Look, I understand how difficult
it was for you after...
...after...
I just let it slide,
Mrs. Hudson, I let it all slide.
And it just got harder and harder
to pick up the phone, somehow.
Do you know what I mean?
(SHE SIGHS)
I need you to give this matter
your full attention, Sherlock,
is that quite clear? What do you
think of this shirt? Sherlock!
I will find your underground
terror cell, Mycroft.
Just put me back in London.
I need to get to know the
place again, breathe it in.
Feel every quiver of
its beating heart.
One of our men died
getting this information.
All the chatter, all
the traffic concurs,
theres going to be a terrorist
strike on London, a big one.
And what about John Watson?
John? Mm. Have you seen him?
Oh, yes,
we meet up every Friday
for fish and chips(!)
Ive kept a weather eye
on him, of course.
We havent been in touch
at all to... prepare him.
No.
Well, well have to
get rid of that.
"We?" He looks ancient.
I cant be seen to be wandering
around with an old man.
I couldnt face letting it out.
(SHE COUGHS)
He never liked me dusting.
No, I know.
So why now? What
changed your mind?
Well, Ive got some news.
Oh, God, is it serious?
What? No, no, Im not ill.
Ive, well, Im...
...moving on.
Youre emigrating?
Nope. Er, no, Ive er...
...I have met someone.
Oh! Ah, lovely.
Yeah. Were getting married.
Well, Im going to ask, anyway.
So soon after Sherlock?
Hmm, well, yes.
What's his name?
Its a woman.
A woman?! Yes, of
course its a woman.
You really have moved on, havent
you? Mrs. Hudson, how many times?
Sherlock was not my boyfriend!
Live and let live,
thats my motto.
Listen to me - I am not gay!
(HE SIGHS)
I think Ill surprise John.
Hell be delighted.
You think so?
Mm, pop into Baker Street, who
knows, jump out of a cake.
Baker Street? He
isnt there any more.
Why would he be? Its
been two years.
Hes got on with his life.
What life? Ive been away.
Wheres he going to be tonight? How
would I know? You always know.
He has a dinner reservation
in the Marylebone Road.
Nice little spot.
They have a few bottles of
the 2000 Saint-Emilion,
though I prefer the 2001.
I think maybe Ill just drop by.
You know, it is just possible
that you wont be welcome.
No, it isnt.
Now, where is it? Wheres what?
You know what.
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACH)
Welcome back, Mr. Holmes.
Thank you.
Blud.
Sir, can I help you?
(MUFFLED SCREAMS)
(PHONE BEEPS)
Your wife just texted you, possibly
her contractions have started.
Excuse me, sir.
Oh, sir, I am so, so sorry.
Er, please, let me just go to the
kitchen and dry that off for you.
Finished with that, sir?
Allow me to take it for you.
Madam, can I suggest you look at
this menu, its completely identical.
IN A FRENCH ACCENT: Can I
help you with anything, sir?
Hi, yeah, Im looking for a
bottle of champagne. A good one.
Hmm, well, these are all
excellent vintages, sir.
Oh, its not really my area,
what do you suggest?
Well, you cannot
possibly go wrong,
but if youd like my personal
recommendation... Hmm?
This last one on the list
is a favourite of mine.
It is, you might in fact say,
like a face from the past.
Great. I'll have
that one please.
It is familiar, but with
the quality of surprise!
Well, surprise me.
Im certainly
endeavouring to, sir.
Sorry that took so long.
You OK?
Yeah, yeah. Me? Fine. I am fine.
(HE CHUCKLES)
Now then, what did
you want to ask me?
More wine? No, Im good
with water, thanks. Right.
So? Er, so...
Mary...
Listen, um...
I know it hasnt been long,
and I know we havent known
each other for a long time...
Go on. Yes, I will.
As you know, these last couple of
years havent been easy for me.
And meeting you...
Yeah, meeting you has
been the best thing
that could have possibly
happened. I agree. What?
I agree, Im the best thing that
could have happened to you.
Sorry. Well, no, its, um...
So...
...if youll have me, Mary,
could you see your way, um...
(HE CLEARS HIS THROAT)
(SHE GIGGLES)
If you could see your way to...
Sir, youll find this vintage
exceptionally to your liking.
It has all the qualities of the
old, with the colour of the new.
No, sorry, not now, please. Like a
gaze from a crowd of strangers,
suddenly one is aware of staring
into the face of an old friend.
No, look, seriously,
could you just...?
Interesting thing, a tuxedo.
Lends distinction to friends
and anonymity to waiters.
John?
John, what is it? What?
Well, the short version...
...not dead.
Bit mean springing it on
you like that, I know.
Could have given you a heart
attack, probably still will.
But in my defence,
it was very funny.
OK, its not a great defence.
Oh, no, youre... Oh, yes.
Oh, my God!
Not quite. You died,
you jumped off a roof.
No. Youre dead.
No, Im quite sure, I checked.
Excuse me.
Does... does yours rub off too?
Oh, my God! Oh, my God!
Do you have any idea
what youve done?!
OK, John, Im suddenly
realising I probably owe you
some sort of an apology...
All right, just,
John, just keep...
(JOHN GASPS)
Two years.
Two years! Hmm?
I thought...
...you were dead.
Hmm?
(JOHN GASPS)
Now, you let me grieve. Hmm.
How could you do that?
How?!
Wait, before you do anything
that you might regret, um,
one question, just let
me ask one question.
Are you really going
to keep that?
MUSIC: "Donde Estas,
Yolanda?" by Pink Martini
I calculated that there
were 13 possibilities
once ID invited
Moriarty onto the roof.
I wanted to avoid dying,
if at all possible.
The first scenario involved hurling myself
into a parked van filled with washing bags.
Impossible, the angle was too steep.
Secondly, a system of Japanese wrestling...
You know, for a genius, you
can be remarkably thick.
What? I don't care how
you faked it, Sherlock.
I want to know why.
Why? Because Moriarty
had to be stopped.
Oh.
Why, as in...?
I see. Yes. Why?
Thats a little more
difficult to explain.
Ive got all night.
(HE CLEARS HIS THROAT)
Actually, um, that was
mostly Mycrofts idea.
Oh, so it was your
brothers plan?
Oh, but he would have
needed a confidante.
Mm-hm.
Sorry.
But he was the only one?
The only one who knew?
A couple of others. It was a very
elaborate plan, it had to be.
The next of the 13
possibilities was... Who else?
Who else knew?
Who?! Molly.
Molly?! John... Molly Hooper
and some of my homeless
network and thats all. OK.
OK.
So just your brother, Molly
Hooper and 100 tramps.
Ha, no! 25 at most.
(GLASS SHATTERS)
Seriously, its not a joke?
Youre really keeping this?
Er, yeah.
Sure?
Mary likes it.
Hmm, no, she doesn't.
She does. She doesn't.
Oh, don't.
Oh, brilliant(!) Look,
Im sorry, Im sorry,
I didn't know how to tell you...
Right, no, no, this is charming.
Ive really missed this(!)
One word, Sherlock, that is
all I would have needed!
One word to let me know
that you were alive!
Ive nearly been in contact so
many times, but... John SCOFFS
I worried that, you know, you might
say something indiscreet. What?
You know, let the cat out of
the bag. So this is my fault!
Oh, God! Why am I the only one
who thinks that this is wrong?!
The only one reacting
like a human being!
Over-reacting. Over-reacting!
John! Over-reacting! So you fake
your own death and you waltz in here
large as bloody life! Shh. But Im not
meant to have a problem with it,
cos Sherlock Holmes thinks its
a perfectly OK thing to do!
Shut up! I don't want everyone
knowing Im still alive!
Oh, so its still a secret, is
it?! Yes, its still a secret!
Promise you wont tell anyone?
Swear to God!
London is in danger, John.
Theres an imminent
terrorist attack and
I need your help.
My help?
You have missed this, admit it.
The thrill of the chase, the blood
pumping through your veins,
just the two of us against
the rest of the world.
I don't understand,
I said Im sorry,
isnt that what youre
supposed to do?
Gosh, you don't know anything
about human nature, do you?
Hmm, nature? No.
Human? No.
I'll talk him round.
You will? Oh, yeah.
Mary.
Can you believe his nerve?
I like him.
What?
(METALLIC SOUND)
Those things will kill you.
Oh, you bastard!
Its time to come back.
Youve been letting
things slide, Graham.
Greg. Greg.
RADIO: Very common belief,
with an anti terrorism bill...
(THUDDING)
...the Government
feels duty-bound
to push through the legislation
with all due exped...
(THUDDING CONTINUES)
(SHE YELLS)
Now, stay exactly
where you are.
Where are you?
Dont move.
Keep your eyes fixed on me.
What? What's happening?
What's going on?
Please, will you do this for me?
Please.
Do what?
This phone call...
its my note.
Thats what people
do, don't they?
Leave a note.
MORIARTY GIGGLES.
Leave a note when?
Goodbye, John. No.
(MORIARTY LAUGHS)
Sherlock!
Oh, ho!
What?! Are you out
of your mind?!
I don't see why not.
Its just as plausible as
some of your theories.
Look, if youre not going to
take it seriously, Laura...
I do take it seriously.
I don't think we
should wear hats.
I founded The Empty Hearse' so
like-minded people could meet,
discuss theories!
Sherlocke still out there.
Im convinced of it.
Oh, my God!
(MOBILE PHONES RING)
Oh... my... God!
"His movements were so silent,"
"so furtive he reminded me"
"of a trained bloodhound
picking out a scent."
You what? "I couldnt help thinking
what an amazing criminal hed make"
"if he turned his talents against
the law." Dont read that.
Famous blog, finally.
Come on, thats...
Ancient history, yes, I know, but its
not though, is it, because hes...
What are you doing?
Having a wash.
Youre shaving it off.
Well, you hate it.
Sherlock hates it.
Apparently everyone hates it.
Oh!
Are you going to see him again?
No, Im going to work.
Oh, and after work, are you
going to see him again? No.
God, I had six months of
bristly kisses for me
and then his nibs turns up...
I don't shave for
Sherlock Holmes.
You should put
that on a T-shirt.
Shut up. Or what?
Or Ill marry you.
London, its like a great
cesspool into which all kinds
of criminals, agents and drifters
are irresistibly drained.
Sometimes its not a question of
who, its a question of who knows?
If this man cancels his
papers, I need to know.
If this woman leaves London without
putting her dog into kennels,
I need to know.
I have certain people,
they are markers.
If they start to move,
I'll know somethings up.
Like rats deserting
a sinking ship.
All very interesting, Sherlock,
but the terror alert has
been raised to critical.
Boring. Your move.
We have solid information,
an attack IS coming.
Solid information, a secret terrorist
organisation is planning an attack...
Thats what secret terrorist organisations
do, isnt it? Its their version of golf.
An agent gave his life to
tell us that. Oh, well,
perhaps he shouldn't have done. He was
obviously just trying to show off.
None of these markers' of yours is
behaving in any way suspiciously?
Your move.
No, Mycroft, but you have to
trust me. I'll find the answer.
But itll be in an odd
phrase in an on-line blog,
or an unexpected trip
to the countryside,
or a misplaced lonely hearts ad.
Your move!
Ive given the Prime Minister my
personal assurance youre on the case.
I am on the case, we both
are, look at us right now.
(BUZZER SOUNDS)
Oh, bugger! Whoopsy!
Cant handle a broken heart.
How very telling.
Dont be smart.
That takes me back.
"Dont be smart, Sherlock,
Im the smart one."
I am the smart one.
I used to think I was an idiot.
Both of us thought you
were an idiot, Sherlock.
We had nothing else to go on,
until we met other children.
Oh, yes, that was a mistake.
Ghastly. What were they thinking of?
Probably something about
trying to make friends.
Oh, yes. Friends.
Of course, you go in for
that sort of thing now.
And you don't? Ever?
If you seem slow
to me, Sherlock,
can you imagine what
real people are like?
Im living in a
world of goldfish.
Yes, but Ive been
away for two years.
So? Oh, I don't know,
I thought perhaps you might
have found yourself a...
goldfish. Change
the subject, now.
Rest assured, Mycroft,
whatever this underground
network of yours is up to,
the secret will reside in something
seemingly insignificant or bizarre.
Ooh-ooh. Speaking of which...
I cant believe it. I
just cant believe it!
Him sitting in his chair again.
Oh, isnt it wonderful,
Mr. Holmes?
I can barely contain myself(!)
Oh, he really can, you know.
Hes secretly pleased to see
you, underneath all that.
Sorry, which of us?
Both of you.
Lets play something different.
Why are we playing games?!
Londons terror alert has
been raised to critical,
Im just passing the time.
Lets do deductions.
Client left this while I was
out, what do you reckon?
Im busy.
Oh, go on, its been an age.
(HE SNIFFS)
I always win. Which is
why you cant resist.
I find nothing irresistible in the
hat of a well-travelled anxious,
sentimental, unfit creature of
habit with appalling halitosis.
Damn. Isolated too,
don't you think?
Why would he be isolated?
"He?" Obviously. Why?
Size of the hat?
Dont be silly. Some women
have large heads too.
No, hes recently
had his hair cut,
you can see the little hairs adhering to
the perspiration stains on the inside.
Some women have short hair too.
Balance of probability. Not
that youve ever spoken
to a woman with short hair,
or, you know, a woman.
Stains show hes out of condition.
Hes sentimental cos the hat
has been repaired, three, four...
Five times. Very neatly.
The cost of the repairs
exceeds that of the hat,
hes mawkishly attached to it.
More than that.
One or two patches would
indicate sentimentality.
Fives obsessive behaviour.
Obsessive compulsive.
Hardly. Your client
left it behind.
What sort of an obsessive
compulsive would do that?
The earlier patches are
extensively sun bleached,
so hes worn it abroad, in Peru.
Peru? This is a chullo.
The classic headgear of
Andes, its made of alpaca.
No. No? Icelandic sheep wool.
Similar, but very distinctive,
if you know what youre looking for.
Ive written a blog on the varying
tensile strengths of
different natural fibres.
Im sure theres a
crying need for that(!)
You said he was anxious? The bobble on
the left side has been badly chewed,
which shows hes a man of a
nervous disposition, but...
But also a creature of habit,
cos he hasnt chewed the bobble
on the right. Precisely.
A sniff of the offending
bobble tells us all
we need to know about the
state of his breath.
Brilliant! Elementary.
But youve missed his isolation.
I don't see it.
Plain as day. Where?
There for all to see. Tell me.
Plain as the nose on your...
Tell me!
Well, anybody who wears
a hat as stupid as this
isnt in the habit of hanging
around other people, is he?
Not at all. Maybe he just
doesn't mind being different.
He doesn't necessarily
have to be isolated.
Exactly.
Im sorry?
Hes different, so what?
Why would he mind?
Youre quite right.
Why would anyone mind?
I am not lonely, Sherlock.
How would you know?
Yes. Back to work, if you
don't mind. Good morning.
(SHE CHUCKLES)
Right, back to work.
(KNOCKING ON THE DOOR)
Mr. Summerson.
Right. Undescended testicle.
Right.
(PHONE BEEPS)
Sherlock? Hmm?
Talk to John.
Ive tried talking to him. He
made his position quite clear.
Just relax, Mr. Summerson.
What did he say?
F... Cough.
Oh, dear.
(INTERCOM BUZZES)
Hi?
Mrs. Reeves. Thrush.
Right.
You wanted to see me?
Yes. Molly...
Yes? Would you...?
Would you like to... Have
dinner? ..Solve crimes?
Um...
Absolutely nothing to be
ashamed of, Mrs. Reeves.
Its very common, but Im
recommending a course of...
Monkey glands, but enough
about Professor Presbury.
Tell us more about your case, Mr. Harcourt.
You sure about this? Absolutely.
Should I be making notes? If it makes you
feel better. Thats what John says he does.
So if Im being John... Youre not
being John, youre being yourself.
Well, absolutely no one should
have been able to empty
that bank account other
than myself and Helen.
Why didn't you assume it was your wife?
Because Ive always had total faith in her.
No, its because YOU emptied it.
Weight-loss, hair dye, Botox, affair.
Lawyer. Next!
This is Mr. Blake. Piles.
Mr. Blake, hi.
And your pen-pals emails
just stopped, did they?
(SHE WHINES)
And you really thought he
was the one, didn't you?
The love of your life?
(SHE CRIES)
Stepfather posing as
on-line boyfriend.
What?
Breaks it off, breaks her heart.
She swears off relationships,
stays at home.
He still has her wage coming in.
Mr. Windibank, you have been
a complete and utter...
Piss pot.
Its nothing to worry about, just a
small infection, by the sound of it.
Dr Verner is your usual GP, yes?
IN A FOREIGN ACCENT: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
He looked after me man and boy.
I run a little shop just on
the corner of Church Street.
Oh. Magazines and DVDs.
Ive brought along a few little
beauties that might interest you...
Tree Worshippers. Oh, thats
a corker. Its very saucy.
And British Birds.
Same sort of thing.
Im fine, thanks.
The Holy War.
Sounds a bit dry, I know,
but theres a nun with all
these holes in her habit...
Jesus! Sherlock.
What? What do you want?
Uh?
Have you come to torment me? What are you
talking about? "What are you talking...?"
What, do you think Im going to
be fooled by this bloody beard?!
Youre crazy! No,
no, no, no, no.
Its not as good as your French!
Not as good as your French.
Its not even a good
disguise, Sherlock!
Where did you get it from,
a bloody joke shop...?!
Oh, my God!
I, I am so sorry.
Please...
Its fine.
(HE CLEARS HIS THROAT)
This ones got us all baffled.
Hmm, I don't doubt it.
(HE SNIFFS)
What is it?
Youre onto something,
arent you?
Maybe.
JOHNS VOICE: Show off!
Shut up, John. What? Hmm?
Nothing.
Hello. Hmm.
Are you sure? Im sure. OK.
Im late for Cath.
I'll see you later.
Bye. Bye.
This going to be your
new arrangement, is it?
Just giving it a go.
Right.
So, John?
Not really in the
picture any more.
(RUMBLING NOISE)
Trains?
Trains.
Male, 40 to 50. Oh, sorry,
did you want to be...?
Er, no, please, be my guest.
You jealous?
Shut up!
It doesn't make sense.
What doesn't?
This skeleton, it cant
be any more than...
MOLLY AND SHERLOCK:
Six months old.
Wow!
"How I Did It, by
Jack the Ripper."
Uh-huh. Thats impossible.
Welcome to my world.
Smart arse!
I wont insult your intelligence
by explaining it to you.
No, please, insult away.
You forgot to put
your collar up.
The corpse is, is
six months old.
Its dressed in a shoddy
Victorian outfit from a museum.
Its been displayed on a
dummy for many years,
in a case facing South-east, judging
from the fading of the fabric.
It was sold off in a fire
damage sale a week ago.
So the whole thing was a fake?
Yes.
Looked so promising.
Facile.
Why would someone go
to all that trouble?
Why indeed, John?
DOORBELL: Mind the gap.
Mind the gap.
Oh. Thanks for hanging onto it.
No problem.
So, what's this all
about, Mr. Shilcott?
My girlfriends a
big fan of yours.
Girlfriend?!
Sorry. Do go on.
I like trains.
Yes... I work on the Tube, on the
District Line, and part of my job
is to wipe the security footage
after its been cleared.
I was just whizzing through and I
found something a bit bizarre.
Now, this was a week ago.
The last train on the Friday
night, Westminster Station.
Now, this man gets
into the last car.
Car? Theyre cars,
not carriages.
Its a legacy of the early American
involvement in the Tube system.
He said he liked trains.
And the next stop, St
James' Park Station.
And...
I thought youd like it.
He gets into the last car at
Westminster. The only passenger.
And the car is empty at
St James' Park Station.
Explain that, Mr. Holmes.
Couldnt he have just jumped off? Theres a
safety mechanism that prevents the doors
from opening in transit.
But theres something else,
the driver of that train
hasnt been to work since.
According to his flatmate, hes on
holiday. Came into some money.
Bought off?
Hmm?
So if the driver of the
train was in on it,
then the passenger did get off.
Theres nowhere he could go.
Its a straight run
on the District Line
between the two stations.
Theres no side tunnels,
no maintenance tunnels.
Nothing on any map. Nothing.
Train never stops
and a man vanishes.
Good, innit?
I know that face.
(JOHN CLEARS HIS THROAT)
Excuse you(!)
The journey between those stations
usually takes five minutes
and that one took ten. Ten minutes to
get from Westminster to St James' Park.
I'll need maps, lots of maps.
Older maps, all the maps. Right.
Fancy some chips? What?
I know a fantastic fish shop
just off the Marylebone Road,
the owner always gives
me extra portions.
Did you get him off
a murder charge?
No, I helped him put
up some shelves.
Sherlock? Hmm?
What was today about?
Saying thank you.
For what?
For everything you did for me.
Its OK. Its my pleasure.
No. I mean it.
I don't mean pleasure,
I mean I didn't mind.
I wanted to... Moriarty slipped
up, he made a mistake.
Because the one person he thought
didn't matter at all to me
was the one person that
mattered the most.
You made it all possible.
But you cant do this
again, can you?
Ive had a lovely day. ID
love to, I just, um...
Hmm, congratulations,
by the way.
Hes not from work.
We met through friends,
old-fashioned way.
Hes nice, weve got a dog, we,
we go to the pub on weekends
and Ive met his mum and dad and
his friends and all his family.
Ive no idea why Im telling
you any of this...
I hope youll be very
happy, Molly Hooper.
You deserve it.
After all, not all the men you fall
for can turn out to be sociopaths.
No? No.
Maybe its just my type.
(HE COUGHS)
(PHONE BEEPS)
Oh, Mrs. Hudson, sorry, I think
someones got John. John Watson?
Hang on, who are you?!
Oh, Im his fiancee.
Oh. Mary?
What's wrong?
Someone sent me this.
At first I thought it
was just a Bible thing,
you know, spam, but its not.
Its a skip code.
First word, then every third.
"Save John Watson."
Now!
Where are we going?
St James The Less, its a church.
20 minutes by car.
Did you drive here? Er, yes.
Its too slow, its too slow.
(CAR HORN HONKS)
Watch out! What are
we waiting for?!
This.
(BRAKES SQUEAL)
What does it mean?
What are they going
to do to him?
I don't know!
(VOICES IN THE BACKGROUND)
(HE GASPS)
Damn!
POLICEMAN: Oi! Oi! You
cant go down there!
(MUFFLED SCREAM)
(HE GASPS)
(HE GAGS)
(HORN HONKS)
No, its not going
to work, with that.
I'll get something to
help it along. Yeah.
Help! Argh!
(MUFFLED SCREAMS)
He doesn't like it, Daddy. Huh?
Guy Fawkes, he doesn't like it.
Stay back, Zoe. Back!
Now.
(HE SCREAMS)
What does it mean?
Oh, my God!
(CHEERING)
Help!
(SHE SCREAMS)
Stand back!
(JOHN GROANS)
Move! Move! Move!
Move! Move!
John! John!
Get up, John!
John! John?!
Help!
John!
John! John!
Hey, John.
ELDERLY LADY: Which wasnt the way
ID put it at all. Silly woman.
Anyway, it was then that I
first noticed it was missing.
I said, "Have you checked
down the back of the sofa?"
Hes always losing things down the
back of the sofa, arent you, dear?
Afraid so.
Oh, keys, small
change, sweeties.
Especially his glasses. Glasses.
Blooming things. I said,
"Why don't you get a chain,"
"wear them round your neck?"
And he says, "What, like Larry
Grayson!" Larry Grayson.
So did you find it eventually,
your lottery ticket?
Well, yes, thank goodness.
We caught the coach
on time after all.
We managed to see St
Pauls, the Tower,
but they werent letting
anyone into Parliament.
Some big debate going on.
(DOOR OPENS)
John? Sorry, youre busy. No, no,
no, they were just leaving.
No, oh, were we? Yes. No,
no, if youve got a case...
No, not a case. Yeah, go.
Were here till
Saturday, remember. Yes,
wonderful. Just get out!
Yes, well, give us a ring.
Very nice, yes, good. Get out!
I cant tell you how
glad we are, Sherlock.
All that time people
thinking the worst.
Were just so pleased
its all over.
Ring up more often, wont you?
Mm-hm. She worries.
Promise?
Promise.
Oh, for God...
(HE SIGHS)
Sorry about that. No, its fine.
Clients?
Just my parents.
Your parents? In
town for a few days.
Your parents? Mycroft promised to
take them to a matinee of Les Mis.
Tried to talk me into doing it.
Those were your parents? Yes.
Well...
...that is not what I...
What?
I mean, they're just so...
...ordinary.
Its a cross I have to bear.
Did they know too?
Hmm? That you spent the last two
years playing hide and seek?
Maybe. Ah, so thats why
they werent at the funeral!
Sorry, sorry again. Hmm.
Sorry.
So youve shaved it off then?
Yeah. Wasnt working for me.
Yeah, Im glad. You
didn't like it?
No, I prefer my
doctors clean-shaven.
Thats not a sentence
you hear every day.
How are you feeling?
Yeah, not bad. Bit smoked.
Right.
Last night, who did that?
And why did they target me?
I don't know.
Is it someone trying to
get to you through me?
Is it something to do with this
terrorist thing you talked about?
I don't know, I cant see the
pattern. Its too nebulous.
Why would an agent give his
life to tell us something
incredibly insignificant?
Thats what's strange.
Give his life?
According to Mycroft.
Theres an underground network planning
an attack on London, thats all we know.
(HE SNIFFS)
These are my rats, John. Rats?
My markers, agents, lowlifes.
People who might find themselves
arrested or their diplomatic
immunity suddenly rescinded.
If one of them starts acting
suspiciously, we know somethings up.
Five of them are behaving perfectly
normally, but the sixth...
I know him, don't I?
Lord Moran, Peer of the Realm.
Minister for Overseas Development.
Pillar of the Establishment.
Yes.
Hes been working for
North Korea since 1996.
What? Hes the big
rat, rat number one.
Hes just done something
very suspicious indeed.
Yeah, thats odd.
Theres nowhere he
could have got off?
Not according to the maps.
Theres something, something,
something Im missing.
Something staring
me in the face.
(PHONE BEEPS)
Any idea who they are,
this underground network?
Intelligence must have a list
of the most obvious ones.
Our rats just come
out of his den.
Al-Qaeda? The IRA have been
getting restless again,
maybe they're going to make an
appearance... Yes, yes, yes, yes!
Ive been an idiot,
a blind idiot!
What? Oh, thats good.
That could be brilliant!
What are you on about? Mycrofts
intelligence is not nebulous at all,
its specific,
incredibly specific.
What do you mean?
Its not an underground network,
John, its an Underground network!
Right.
What? Sometimes a deception is
so audacious, so outrageous
that you cant see it even when its
staring you in the face. Look,
seven carriages leave
Westminster. Mm.
And only six carriages
arrive at St James' Park.
Ah, but thats, I mean,
its impossible.
Moran didn't disappear. The
entire tube compartment did.
The driver must have diverted the train
and then detached the last carriage.
Detached it where? You said there
was nothing between those stations.
Not on the maps, but once you
eliminate the other factors,
the remaining thing must be the truth. That
carriage vanished, so it must be somewhere.
But why, though?
Why detach it in
the first place?
It vanishes between St
James' Park and Westminster.
Lord Moran vanishes.
Youre kidnapped and nearly burnt
to death at a fireworks party.
What's the date,
John, todays date?
Hmm? November the...
Oh, God!
Lord Moran, hes a
Peer of the Realm.
Normally hed sit in the House.
Tonight, theres an all-night sitting to
vote on the new anti-terrorism bill.
But he wont be
there, not tonight.
Not the 5th November.
"Remember, remember..."
"Gunpowder, treason and plot!"
Theres nothing down there,
Mr. Holmes, I told you.
No sidings, no ghost stations.
There has to be, check again.
This whole area is a big
mess of old and new stuff.
Charing Cross is made up
of bits of older stations,
like Trafalgar Square, Strand.
No, its none of those,
weve accounted for those.
St Margaret Street, Bridge Street,
Sumatra Road, Parliament Street...
Hang on, hang on, Sumatra Road?
You mentioned Sumatra Road,
Mr. Holmes? There is something,
I knew it rang a bell! Yes.
There was a station down there.
Well, why isnt it on the maps?
Because it was closed before
it ever opened.' What?
They built the platforms, even the
staircases, but it all got tied up
in legal disputes and so they never
built the station on the surface.
Its right underneath the
Palace of Westminster.
So what's down there, a bomb?
Oh.
With many commentators saying
the vote on the Terrorism Bill
will be too close to call,
MPs are now making their way
into the Chamber for what
the Government is calling "the most
important vote of this Parliament."
Over now to our...
What freedoms exactly
are we protecting
if we start spying
on our own people?
This is a Orwellian measure
on a scale unprecedented...
Theres a bomb, then? The tube
carriage is carrying a bomb.
Must be. Right.
What are you doing? Im calling
the police. What? No!
Sherlock, this isnt a game, they
need to evacuate Parliament.
Theyll get in the way, they always
do. This is cleaner, more efficient.
And illegal? A bit.
What are you doing?
Coming.
I don't understand.
Well, thats a first.
Theres nowhere
else it could be.
(SCREAMING)
Oh!
What?!
Hang on, Sherlock...? What?
Thats, isnt it live?
Perfectly safe as long as we
avoid touching the rails.
Of course, yeah, avoid
the rails. Great!
This way.
Are you sure? Sure.
Ha!
Look at that.
John... Hmm?
Demolition charges.
Its empty. Theres nothing.
Isnt there?
This is the bomb.
What?
Its not carrying explosives, the
whole compartment is the bomb.
(HE GASPS)
We need bomb disposal.
There may not be
time for that now.
So what do we do?
I have no idea.
Well, think of something. Why
do you think I know what to do?
Cos youre Sherlock Holmes,
youre as clever as it gets.
It doesn't mean I know how
to diffuse a giant bomb!
What about you?! I wasnt in bomb
disposal, Im a bloody doctor!
And a soldier, as you
keep reminding us all!
Cant... Cant we rip the
timer off, or something?
That would set it off. You
see, you know things!
(BEEPING)
Oh!
Er... My God!
Er...
(JOHN GASPS)
Why didn't you call the police?!
Can you just...? Why do you
never call the police?!
Well, its no use now.
So you cant switch
the bomb off?!
You cant switch the bomb off and
you didn't call the police!
Go, John. Go now!
Theres no point now, is there,
because theres not enough time
to get away and if we don't do
this, other people will die!
(SHERLOCK SIGHS)
Mind palace!
Hmm? Use your mind palace!
How will that help?
Youve salted away every
fact under the sun!
And you think Ive just
got "how to defuse a"
"bomb" tucked away in
there somewhere?! Yes!
Maybe.
Think!
Think, please think.
I cant!
Oh, my God!
This is it.
Um, er...
(SHERLOCK BREATHES HEAVILY)
Oh, my God!
Turn that off. Oh, God!
Er, um, er...
Im sorry.
What?
I cant, I cant do it, John.
I don't know how.
Forgive me.
What?!
Please, John, forgive me,
for all the hurt
that I caused you.
No, no, no, no, no, no,
this is a trick. No.
Another one of your
bloody tricks.
No. Youre just trying to
make me say something nice.
Not this time.
Its just to make you look good
even though youve behaved like...
I wanted you not to be dead.
Yeah, well, be careful
what you wish for.
If I hadnt come back, you wouldnt
be standing there and...
...youd still have a
future, with Mary.
Yeah, I know.
Look, I find it difficult. I find
it difficult, this sort of stuff.
I know.
You were the best and the wisest
man that I have ever known.
Yes, of course I forgive you.
The criminal network
Moriarty headed was vast.
Its roots were everywhere, like a
cancer, so we came up with a plan.
Mycroft fed Moriarty
information about me.
Moriarty, in turn,
gave us hints,
just hints as to the
extent of his web.
We let him go, because it was
important to let him believe
he had the upper hand.
And then, I sat back
and watched Moriarty
destroy my reputation,
bit by bit.
I had to make him
believe hed beaten me,
utterly defeated me, and
then hed show his hand.
There were 13 likely scenarios
once we were up on that roof.
Each of them were rigorously
worked out and given a code name.
It wasnt just my reputation
that Moriarty needed to bury.
I had to die.
Sherlock!
You can have me arrested,
you can torture me,
you can do anything
you like with me,
but nothings going to prevent
them from pulling the trigger.
Your only three friends in the
world will die, unless...
Unless I kill myself and
complete your story.
Youve got to admit
thats sexier.
But the one thing I didn't
anticipate was just how far.
Moriarty was prepared to go.
I suppose that was obvious,
given our first meeting
at the swimming pool.
His death wish.
Argh!
(GUNSHOT)
I knew I didn't have long.
I contacted my brother,
set the wheels in motion.
And then everyone got to work.
Its a trick.
Its just a magic trick.
All right, stop it now.
Now, stay exactly
where you are.
Dont move!
All right.
Keep your eyes fixed on me.
Please, will you do this for me?
It was vital that John
stayed just where ID put him
and that way his view was blocked
by the ambulance station.
Sherlock!
I needed to hit the air-bag,
which I did.
Speed was Paramount.
The air-bag needed to
be got out of the way
just as John cleared
the station.
But we needed him to see a body.
Thats where Molly came in.
Like figures on a weather clock, we
went one way, John went the other.
Then, our well-timed cyclist...
...put John briefly
out of action,
giving me time to switch places
with the corpse on the pavement.
The rest was just
window dressing.
And one final touch, a squash
ball under the armpit.
Apply enough pressure and it
momentarily cuts off the pulse.
Let me come through, please!
Its all right...
No, hes my friend.
Its all right. No,
hes my friend.
Its all right, its all right...
Hes my friend, please.
Everything was anticipated,
every eventuality allowed for.
It worked perfectly.
Molly. Molly Hooper?
She was in on it?
Yes. You remember the little girl
who was abducted by Moriarty?
(SHE SCREAMS)
Get out!
You assumed she reacted like that
because I was her kidnapper.
But I deduced Moriarty must
have found someone who looked
very like me to plant suspicion,
and that that man, whoever he was,
had to be got out of the way as
soon as his usefulness ended.
That meant there was a corpse
in the morgue somewhere
that looked just like me.
Clever.
Molly found the body,
faked the records
and I provided the other coat.
Ive got lots of coats.
What about the sniper
aiming at John?
Mycrofts men intervened before
he could take the shot.
He was invited to reconsider.
(TELEPHONE RINGS)
Is it done?
Good.
And your homeless network?
As I explained, the whole
street was closed off.
Like a scene from a play.
Neat, don't you think?
Hmm...
What?
Not the way ID have done it.
Oh, really?
No, Im not saying its not
clever, but... What?
Bit... disappointed.
Oh. Everyones a critic.
Anyway, thats not why I came.
No? No, I think you know
why Im here, Phillip.
"How I Did It, by
Jack the Ripper?"
Didnt you think it
was intriguing?
Lurid. A case so sensational
you hoped ID be interested.
But you overdid it, Phillip.
You and your little fan-club.
I just couldnt live with myself,
knowing that ID driven you to...
But you didn't. You were
always right, I wasnt dead.
No. No, and everything's
OK now, isnt it?
Yeah. Yeah.
Though of course youve
wasted police time.
Perverted the course of justice.
Risked distracting me from a massive
terrorist assault that could have
both destroyed Parliament and caused
the death of hundreds of people.
Oh, God! Oh, God,
Im sorry, Sherlock!
Im so sorry. HE CRIES.
Hang on.
That doesn't make sense.
How could you be sure John would
stand on that exact spot?
I mean, what if hed moved?
And... how did you do
it all so quickly?
What if the bike hadnt hit him?
And anyway, why are you
telling me all this?
(HE CHUCKLES)
If youd pulled that off, Im the
last person youd tell the truth to!
Sherlock Holmes!
(SHERLOCK GIGGLES)
You... Oh, your face!
...utter... Your face!
You!
Totally had you! You cock!
I knew it! I knew it! You... Oh, those
things you said, such sweet things.
I never knew you cared. I will, Ill kill
you if you ever breathe a word of this...
Scouts honour... to anyone!
You knew!
You knew how to turn it off!
Theres an off switch.
Theres always an off switch.
Terrorists can get into
all sorts of problems
unless theres an off switch.
So why did you let me go through all
that?! I didn't lie altogether.
Ive absolutely no idea how to turn any
of these silly little lights off.
(SHERLOCK GIGGLES)
(NOISE FROM WALKIE TALKIES)
And you did call the police?
Of course I called the police.
Im definitely going
to kill you!
Oh, please. Killing me,
thats so two years ago.
(SHERLOCK LAUGHS)
(GUN COCKS)
MUSIC: "Do You Hear The People
Sing" from Les Miserables.
MYCROFT: Sherlock,
please, I beg of you.
You can take over
at the interval.
Oh, Im sorry, brother dear,
but you made a promise.
Nothing I can do to help.
But you don't understand the
pain of it, the horror.
Come on, youll have to go
down, they want the story.
In a minute.
Im really pleased, Mary.
Have you set a date?
Well, we thought May. Ah,
a spring wedding. Yeah.
Well, once weve actually
got engaged. Yeah.
We were interrupted last time.
Yeah. Well, I cant wait.
You will be there, Sherlock?
Weddings, not really my thing.
Hello, everyone. Hello, Molly.
This is Tom. Tom,
this is everyone. Hi.
Hi. Its really nice
to meet you all. Hi.
Wow! Yeah, hi, Im John,
good to meet you.
Ready? Ready.
Champagne?
Yes.
Thanks.
Thank you.
Sit down, love. Oh, thanks.
So um...
Is it serious, you two?
Yeah. Ive moved on.
Did you...?
Im not saying a word.
No, best not.
But Im still waiting. Hmm?
Why did they try and kill me?
If they knew you were onto
them, why come after me?
Put me in a bonfire?
I don't know. I don't
like not knowing.
Unlike the nicely embellished
fictions on your blog, John,
real life is rarely so neat.
I don't know who was behind all
this, but I will find out,
I promise you.
Dont pretend youre
not enjoying this.
Hmm? Being back.
Being a hero again.
Dont be stupid. Youd have to
be an idiot not to see it.
You love it. Love what?
Being Sherlock Holmes.
I don't even know what
thats supposed to mean.
Sherlock, you are going to
tell me how you did it?
How you jumped off that
building and survived?
You know my methods, John, I
am known to be indestructible.
No, but seriously.
When you were dead, I
went to your grave.
I should hope so.
I made a little speech.
I actually spoke to you.
I know. I was there.
I asked you for
one more miracle.
I asked you to stop being dead.
I heard you.
Anyway, time to go and
be Sherlock Holmes.
(CAMERAS SNAP)
SHERLOCKS VOICE: John!
MARYS VOICE: John!
John!